<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">
<chapter>
  <header>
    <title>Mnesia Database Questions</title>
    <prepared>Matthias Lang</prepared>
<docno></docno>
<date>2007-09-12</date>
    <rev>1.0</rev>
  </header>

<p>

Mnesia is the somewhat odd name for the real-time, distributed database which
comes with Erlang. 

</p>
<section><title>What is Mnesia good at?</title>

	<section> <title>Locking and Transactions</title>
	<p>
	If you need to keep a database that will be used by multiple 
	processes and/or nodes, using Mnesia means you don't have
	to write your own access controls.
	</p></section>

	<section> <title>Distribution</title>
	<p>

	Tables can be replicated at many nodes, both for efficiency
	(database lookup is a local activity) and robustness 
	(redundancy means if one node goes down, other nodes still 
	have copies of the data.)
	</p></section>

	<section> <title>Non-fully-normalised data</title>
        <p>
	Unlike most database systems, records can contain data 
	of arbitrary size and structure.
	</p></section>

	<section><title>Monitoring</title>
	<p>
	Monitoring - processes can subscribe to events which are 
	sent when various operations on the data take place 
	(update, delete, etc)  The RDBMS package allows even 
	more fine-grained control.
	</p></section>

</section>
<section><title>What is Mnesia not so good at?</title>
<p>

	Mnesia is primarily intended to be a memory-resident database.
	Some of its design tradeoffs reflect this.

</p><p>
	Really large tables must be stored in a fragmented manner.

</p></section>
<section><title>Is Mnesia good for storing blobs?</title>
<p>

	It depends. Erlang has no problem storing Erlang binary data
	types of arbritary size,  however due to the in-memory-database 
	design emphasis of mnesia, storing lots of binary 
	data will eventually hit one of a number of limitations. 
	These are driven by:
</p>

	<list>
	<item><p>
	
	Storage type - Both <c>ram_copies</c> and 
	<c>disc_copies</c> tables 
	rely on storing a full copy of the whole table and data 
	in main memory. This will limit total blob storage to 
	the size of available memory.
	</p><p>

	On the other hand <c>disc_only_copies</c>
	 tables do not suffer 
	from this limitation but they are slow (from disk) and 
	the data is stored in dets tables which if not closed 
	properly (e.g. after system crash) can take a long time 
	to repair (this was improved in recent versions but is 
	still not quick).
        </p></item>
	
	<item><p>
	Replication - if the table has a replica then updating 
	an entry and rebuilding after a restart will copy the 
	data over the network between the two machines. Depending 
	on available bandwidth and the uptime requirements
	this may or may not be acceptable.
        </p></item>
	</list>

	<p>
	
	As always, measurement of the different mechanisms for your 
	specific application is recommended.

	</p><p>
	A more colourful discussion of the these topics can be found
	in this	<url href="http://erlang.org/pipermail/erlang-questions/1999-October/000618.html">
	post to the mailing list.</url>

</p></section>
<section><title>Is there an SQL interface for mnesia?</title>
<p>

	A partial one was built as a masters project, it's
	of limited use and not widely used.

</p><p>
	QLC is the query engine for Mnesia and ETS. It is
	a much better fit to Erlang than SQL.

</p></section>
<section><title>How much data can be stored in Mnesia?</title>
<p>

	Dets uses 32 bit integers for file offsets, so the 
	largest possible mnesia table (for now) is 4Gb.
	</p><p>
	In practice your machine will slow to a crawl way before
	you reach this limit.

</p></section>
<section><title>Contributors</title>
<p> Thanks to Chris Pressey, Ulf Wiger and Sean Hinde for writing
	the entries in this section.
</p></section></chapter>
