<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">
<chapter>
  <header>
    <title>Obtaining Erlang/OTP and books/articles about it</title>
    <prepared>Matthias Lang</prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date>2007-09-12</date>
    <rev>1.0</rev>
    <file>obtaining.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section><title>Where can I get Erlang/OTP?</title>

    <p>
	Open Source Erlang/OTP can be downloaded from
	<url href="http://www.erlang.org/">the open source Erlang
	site</url>. The site provides full source code as well
	as binaries for Windows machines. This is probably the best
	place to go to make sure you're getting the latest version.
</p><p>
        Erlang Solutions provide
	<url href='https://www.erlang-solutions.com/resources/download.html'>binaries</url>
	for a variety of platforms
	(Ubuntu, CentOS, MacOS X, Debian, Windows, Fedora and Raspian).

</p><p>

	The <url href="http://www.debian.org/">Debian
	Distribution</url> of <em>GNU/Linux</em>, and derivatives such
	as Ubuntu, includes various versions Erlang in different
	releases, under <em>interpreters</em>. The version tends to
	lag a long way behind Erlang Solutions' package (above).
</p><p>
	For the BSDs, the 'ports' collection has up to date versions of
	Erlang.
</p><p>
	Users within Ericsson can use Ericsson's internally supported
        version of Erlang from <url href="http://www.erlang.se/">
	www.erlang.se</url>.
</p>
  </section>

  <section><title>What's the current version of (Open Source) Erlang?</title>

	<p>Erlang/OTP 19.0 was released in June 2016.</p>

	<p>Prior to 17.0, Erlang used a slightly unusual version
	numbering scheme, e.g. the previous version was called R16B-3.

	</p><p>Major releases typically come somewhere between 12
	and 18 months apart.

	</p><p>
	Components of Erlang have their own version numbers, for
	instance the virtual machine in 17.0 has version 6.0.
        </p>
  </section>

  <section><title> Which licence is Open Source Erlang shipped with?</title>

    <p>
	The Open Source Erlang <url
	href="http://www.erlang.org/EPLICENSE">Licence</url> is essentially
	the Mozilla (Netscape) Public Licence with a few modifications
	to make it compatible with Swedish law.
	</p><p>

	As far as I understand, this means you can obtain Erlang
	for free, use it to build cool systems and sell them
	without Ericsson coming around to charge you money.
	For an authoritative statement, you'll need a lawyer.
</p>
  </section>

  <section><title>Where is the Erlang documentation?</title>

    <p>
        The language itself is best described by the
	<url href="http://www.erlang.org/doc/reference_manual/users_guide.html">
        Language Reference Manual</url>.</p><p>

	The documentation delivered with open source erlang,
	as both man pages and <url href="http://www.erlang.org/doc.html">
	html</url>, is the most up-to-date reference to both the
	OTP libraries and Erlang itself. On unix systems,
	an easy way to read the man pages is <c>erl -man gen_tcp
	</c>.
      </p>
  </section>

  <section><title>Which book about Erlang should I read?</title>

  <p>Different books are aimed at different audiences, so recommending
  one in particular is difficult. The currently available books in
  English, starting with the most recently published, are:
  </p>

	<p>
        <em>Introducing Erlang</em> by Simon St. Laurent, 2013,
        is a very gentle introduction to Erlang for beginners.
        It's available directly from the <url
        href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920025818.do">publisher</url>.
	</p>


	<p>
        <em>Learn You Some Erlang for Great Good!</em> by Fred Hebert
        is a beginners' book about Erlang, published in 2013. It's
        available directly from the <url
        href="http://nostarch.com/erlang">publisher</url> and also
	for reading <url href="http://learnyousomeerlang.com">online</url>.
	</p>


	<p>
        <em>Erlang and OTP in Action </em> by Martin Logan, Eric
        Merritt and Richard Carlsson was published in 2010. You can
        buy it from various online bookstores, or directly from the
        <url href="http://www.manning.com/logan/">publisher</url>.
	</p>

	<p>
        <em>Erlang Programming (A Concurrent Approach to Software
        Development) </em> by Francesco Cesarini and Simon Thompson
        was published in 2009. Get it from Amazon etc or directly from
        the <url
        href="http://oreilly.com/catalog/9780596518189">publisher</url>.
	</p>

	<p>
	<em>Programming Erlang: Software for a Concurrent World</em>
	(Joe Armstrong) is a book about Erlang written by one of the
	original inventors, published in 2007. You can buy it on paper
	from Amazon and other online bookstores, or directly from
	the <url href="http://pragmaticprogrammer.com/titles/jaerlang/index.html">publisher</url>.

	</p><p>

	There are also some books in languages other than English:

	</p><p>
	French: <em>Erlang Programmation</em> (Micka&euml;l R&eacute;mond)
        can be ordered
        <url href="http://www.eyrolles.com/Informatique/Livre/9782212110791/livre-erlang.php">from the publisher</url> or via
	<url href="http://www.amazon.com/">Amazon</url>.

	</p><p> Spanish: <em>Erlang/OTP Un Mundo Concurrente</em>
	(Manuel Rubio) can be ordered directly from the <url
	href='http://erlang.bosqueviejo.net'>publisher</url>.
	</p><p>


	Of historical interest only: <em>Concurrent Programming in
	Erlang (2nd. Edition, 1993)</em> (Armstrong, Virding,
	Wikstr&ouml;m &amp; Williams). Archaeologists can download the
	<url href="http://www.erlang.org/doc.html"> first half of the
	book</url> from erlang.org.

        </p><p>

	Also only of historical interest: Maurice Castro's book, <url
	href="http://www.castro.aus.net/~maurice/serc/erlbk/"
        >Erlang in Real Time (1998)</url>.
	</p>
  </section>

  <section><title> What advanced Erlang documentation is there?</title>

    <p>
      The only way to keep completely up to date with Erlang internals
      is to examine the source code. This section lists some material
      which can help with understanding the code, but keep in mind that
      they all age, i.e. the article/paper/presentation describes the
      code as it was at a particular moment, which is often some
      time ago.
    </p>

    <p>
	The <url href="http://www.erlang.org/download/erl_spec47.ps.gz">
	Standard Erlang</url> spec (1999) aims to define the Erlang language.
	There is currently no compiler which actually implements everything
	exactly the way <em>Standard Erlang</em> specifies.
	This specification is quite precise; it's intended as a reference,
	not a bedtime read! Compiler and tool implementors will find
	this useful, as will advanced Erlang programmers.

</p><p>
	<url href="http://www.it.uu.se/research/group/hipe/cerl/">Core Erlang
	</url> (2004) is an effort to define an Erlang-like language which is
	nicer to compilers and language tools and can be automatically
	generated from Erlang. Erlang compilers from R10 onwards can
	generate Core Erlang from normal Erlang code. They can also
	generate .beam files from Core Erlang.

</p><p>
	The proceedings from the
	<url href='http://www.erlang-factory.com/'>Erlang User Conferences
	</url> contain many interesting articles. The
	<url href="http://www.erlang.se/euc/">
	proceedings</url> for conferences from 1999 to 2008 are also still
	online.

</p><p>
	The internals of the BEAM file format are described on
	<url href="http://www.erlang.se/~bjorn">
	Bj&ouml;rn's homepage (2000) </url>. Eventually
	this will/might include a description of the
	virtual machine's instructions. Bj&ouml;rn also includes some
	benchmarks comparing different versions of the BEAM machine.
	You may also want to take a look at the <c>beam_lib</c>
	module.

</p><p>
	Joe Armstrong's Thesis,
        <url href="http://erlang.org/download/armstrong_thesis_2003.pdf">
	  (2003)
	Making reliable distributed systems in the presence of software errors</url> contains a lot of interesting information, including a compact overview
        of the language, a number of case studies and some discussion of
        the language's evolution, somewhat similar to Bjarne
        Stroustrup's <em>Design and Evolution of C++</em>.

</p><p>
        <url href="http://www.erlang.se/publications/xjobb/Secure_Dist_Comm_in_SafeErlang.pdf">
        Secure Distributed Communication in SAFEERLANG</url> (2000), which was
	a student thesis, contains a good, if dated,
        overview of Erlang's distribution mechanisms (Section 5).
</p><p>
        <url href="http://www.erlang.se/publications/xjobb/d95-rgr.thesis.2s.pdf">
        Enhancing Security in Distributed Erlang by Integrating Access Control</url> (2000) contains a good
        overview of some of Erlang's implementation aspects, including
        memory allocation (section 7).
</p><p>
        The <url href="http://www.cs-lab.org/papers.html">
	(Ex-Ericsson) computer science laboratory</url> has a collection
	of papers about Erlang-related topics.

</p><p>
	The source-code release includes a directory with some of the
	internal build documentation in the subdirectory
	<c>erts/emulator/internal_doc/
	</c>.

</p><p>
    <url href="http://www.erlang-in-anger.com">
    Stuff Goes Bad: Erlang in Anger</url> (2014) contains tips and
    tricks to help understand where failures come from in production
    Erlang systems, with pointers on how to debug and solve them live.
</p>
  </section>

  <section><title> What documentation is there in related subjects?</title>

  <p>
    There are a couple of books about specific types of applications
    which use Erlang as the main language in the book:

  </p><p>
  <em>Building Web Applications with Erlang</em> by Zachary Kessin
  </p><p>
  <em>Handbook of Neuroevolution Through Erlang</em> by Gene I. Sher
  </p><p>

	The standard text about data structures in functional languages
	is <em>Purely Functional Data Structures</em> by
	Chris Okasaki. The parts about laziness (about half of the book)
	do not apply to Erlang, but are interesting nonetheless.
	An <url href="http://www-2.cs.cmu.edu/~rwh/theses/okasaki.pdf">early
	version of the book</url> is available online, the book itself is
	available from many online booksellers.

</p><p>
	<em>Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</em>
	is a standard introductory text to functional programming. It is
	available both on paper and
	<url href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/">online</url>.

</p>
  </section>

  <section><title>Is there public CVS/Git/your-favourite-vcs repository for the Erlang source?</title>

    <marker id="repositories"/>

    <p>As of R13B03 (November 2009), there is
      an <url href="http://github.com/erlang/otp">official Git
      repository</url> maintained (daily!) by the Erlang/OTP
      group. There is also
      an <url href="http://github.com/mfoemmel/erlang-otp"> unofficial
      repository</url> which includes history before the R13B03
      release.
    </p>

  </section>

  <section><title>How can I contribute to Erlang?</title>

    <p>
When you write Erlang code you want to share, there are quite a number of
ways to share it. The place to announce such things is the Erlang Questions
mailing list, or, in the case of patches, the Erlang Patches mailing list.
Where you put the actual code is up to you.

</p><p> If your code is a correction, modification or extension to an
existing part of OTP, the usual way of spreading it is via
<url href="https://github.com/erlang/otp/wiki/Contribution-Guidelines">github</url>.</p>

    <p>
If your code is a new application or library, some common ways of
distributing it are:
</p>

    <list>
      <item><p>Starting your own
      <url href="http://github.com/">github</url>
      or <url href="http://code.google.com/projecthosting/">Google code</url>
      project </p></item>

      <item><p>Putting the code on a personal homepage </p></item>

    </list>
  </section>
  <section>
    <marker id="eeps"/>
    <title>How can I propose changes to the language itself?</title>
    <p>
        Even though Erlang is a fairly mature language with a large
        established code-base, changes and enhancements are still
        being incorporated. There is a mechanism
        called the <url
        href="http://www.erlang.org/erlang-enhancement-proposals">Erlang
        Enhancement Proposal</url> which formalises the process.

</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Where is Erlang discussed in the real world?</title>

    <section>
      <title>Conferences</title><p>

      <url href="http://www.erlang-factory.com">Erlang Factory</url>
      organises regular Erlang conferences around the world. By tradition,
      the annual Erlang User Conference is held in May in Stockholm
      (Erlang's birthplace).
</p><p>
      Erlang crops up in other conferences every so often, e.g.
      <url href="https://thestrangeloop.com/">Strange Loop</url>
      usually has a presentation or two about Erlang.
</p><p>
        Academic conferences about
	functional programming are also attended by a few Erlang users.
	The <url href="http://icfpconference.org/">
	International Conference on Functional Programming</url> usually
	includes an Erlang workshop.
</p>
  </section>
  <section>
     <title>Erlounge and User Groups</title><p> Every so often,
        someone puts out an invitation on erlang-questions to
        informally discuss Erlang over a few beers. Past Erlounges
        have been in Sweden (Stockholm), Scotland, the USA (Atlanta,
	New York, Chicago, North
        Carolina, Schaumburg, Seattle, SF Bay area,
        Arlington, Washington DC), France (Paris), China (I can't read the
        characters which described the location), Italy, Germany (Aachen),
        Poland (Krakow), New Zealand (Wellington) and others. There's a
        <url href="http://erlangcentral.org/wiki/index.php/ErlangUserGroups">wiki page on erlangcentral.org</url> listing known usergroups.</p>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="mailing-lists"/>
    <title>Where is Erlang discussed online?</title>

    <p>

	There are several
        <url href="http://www.erlang.org/static/doc/mailinglist.html">
	mailing lists devoted to Erlang</url>:
	</p>

    <section>
      <title>erlang-questions</title><p>

		This is intended for general
		discussion about Erlang. Anyone can send
		mail to <url href="mailto:erlang-questions@erlang.org">
		erlang-questions@erlang.org</url>, and anyone can
		<url href="http://www.erlang.org/static/doc/mailinglist.html">
                subscribe</url>.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>erlang-announce</title><p>

		This list carries announcements
		about new releases of Erlang, patches, etc.
		All posts to <em>erlang-announce</em> also appear
		in <em>erlang-questions</em>.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>erlang-patches</title><p>
		This list is for patches to the Erlang distribution.
		At the time of writing, it is not archived.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>erlang-bugs</title><p>
		This list is for bug reports.</p>
    </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="forums"/>
    <title>Web forums and mailing list archives</title>
    <p>

	The erlang-questions list is
	<url href="http://www.erlang.org/pipermail/erlang-questions/">
	archived on the Erlang website</url>.

        </p><p>
        The GMANE news/mail gateway acts as both an archive and a
        forum-style way of using the mailing list. It has
        <url href="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.lang.erlang.general">
	Erlang Questions</url> and
	<url href="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.comp.lang.erlang.patches">
	Erlang Patches</url>.

        </p>

	<p>
	  <url href='http://www.erlangcentral.org'>Erlang Central</url>
	  has some Erlang-related forums. It also has a good calendar of
	  Erlang events (hack nights, local meetups, etc.)
	</p>
  </section>


    <section>
      <title>IRC channel</title><p>
        There's an IRC channel, #erlang, on irc.freenode.net</p>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section><title>Where can I find Erlang programmers/employers?</title>
    <p>
	Posting a short note to <seealso marker="#mailing-lists">
	erlang-questions@erlang.org</seealso> is a good start,
	especially if the subject-line clearly identifies the post as
	a job request/advert.</p>

	<p>
	  There are several sites with a high concentration of Erlang jobs:
	</p>

        <list>
	  <item><url href="http://functionaljobs.com/">Functional Jobs
	  </url></item>

	  <item><url href="https://www.erlang-solutions.com/about/careers.html">
	  Erlang-solutions' recruitment page</url></item>
	</list>

	<p>

	Several consultant groups have Erlang-certified people,
	including <url
	href="http://www.erlang-solutions.com/">erlang-solutions.com
	</url> (based in London, take assignments worldwide), <url
	href="http://www.process-one.net/en/services/">
	Process-one</url> (based in France) and <url
	href="http://www.enea.se/"> ENEA data</url> (Sweden)


	</p><p>
	If you want to be listed here, send some mail to
	<url href="mailto:matthias@corelatus.com">
	matthias@corelatus.com</url>.
	</p><p>

	Kontakten (Contact), an Ericsson-internal newspaper, may
	also be useful as it carries many job ads.
        </p>
  </section>
</chapter>
